Guide to the Henry Stevens Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Henry Stevens papers
1712-1879
1834-1879
MS 1117
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
Correspondence, chiefly concerning books and cataloguing; an essay on the Universal Postal Union; a portion of a speech; an eighteenth-century French manuscript; and memorabilia. Among Henry Stevens' correspondents are John R. Bartlett, Charles Deane, Charles Coffin Jewett, Henry Coit Kingsley, and J. Wingate Thornton.
Stevens, Henry, Jr., 1819-1886
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Henry Stevens, 1847; of Roland A. L. Tree, 1935; and of the estate of Andrew Keogh, 1953.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Henry Stevens was born on August, 24, 1819, in Barnet, Vermont. He attended Middlebury College for a year, but graduated from Yale College in 1843 with the degree of B.A. Upon graduating, he attended Harvard Law School for a year. In 1840, he worked as a clerk in Washington, D.C. for the the treasury department of the United States Senate. He also worked for the Smithsonian Institution and the Library of Congress and was an early advocate for the use of photography as a means of supplementing bibliographies. In 1845, he moved to London, England where he was an agent for the British Museum. Stevens was an expert in early editions of the English Bible and early voyages to America. He died in South Hampstead, England, on February 28, 1886.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, chiefly concerning books and cataloguing; an essay on the Universal Postal Union; a portion of a speech; an eighteenth-century French manuscript; and memorabilia. Among Henry Stevens' correspondents are John R. Bartlett, Charles Deane, Charles Coffin Jewett, Henry Coit Kingsley, and J. Wingate Thornton.
Cataloging; Libraries; Librarians; Bartlett, John Russell, 1805-1886; Deane, Charles, 1813-1889; Jewett, Charles C. (Charles Coffin), 1816-1868; Kingsley, Henry Coit, 1815-1886; Stevens, Henry, Jr., 1819-1886; Thornton, John Wingate, 1818-1878
- Inventory
  Scope and Contents
  The papers of Henry Stevens consist of eleven letters concerning books and cataloging, two short writings and a manuscript advertisement by Henry Stevens, and a few other miscellaneous items. The papers were given to Yale University in separate gifts by Henry Stevens (1847), Roland A. L. Tree (1935), and the estate of Andrew Keogh (1953).
  - Henry Stevens, outgoing letters, with enclosed engraving of H.S., 1852 June 8, 1861 April 6 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Incoming letters
    - American Antiquarian Society, 1877 March 30 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bartlett, John R., 1875 November 5, December 14 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Deane, Charles, 1876 December 12, 1877 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Jewett, Charles Coffin, 1852 December 19 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Kingsley, Henry Coit, 1875 November 24 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Thornton, J. Wingate, 1875 December 9 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - U.S., Library of Congress, 1875 June 25 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "The Universal Postal Union" (MS), [pre-1879] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Partial draft of address to "Mr. President" (MS), undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Beauties of Writing..." (MS advertisement), 1839 December 12 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - La vie & les actions en abbregéde tous les grandes hommes..., 1712 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Calling card of Ronald A. L. Tree, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)